When it comes to diet
and cognitive decline
I talked previously
about glycotoxins,
which are created when high fat,
high protein foods are exposed
to high dry heat
like broiling or roasting.
In this video, we look at endotoxins
which are inflammatory components
of bacteria that can end up
in our blood stream.
How might  the presence
of these toxins
relate to Alzheimers?
Watch to find out.
"The Role of Endotoxins in
Alzheimer’s and Dementia"
Having a high cholesterol level
in your early 40s is associated
with an increased risk of Alzheimer's
and vascular dementia decades later.
And your cholesterol doesn’t have to be
that high to increase dementia risk.
A 57 percent higher risk
of developing Alzheimer's
at a total cholesterol of 240
compared to under 200.
I’ve done a bunch of videos
talking about the clogging
of the cerebral arteries
inside of the brain
with the same atherosclerosis
that causes heart attacks and strokes,
choking off blood flow to the
memory centers in the brain.
This may be why higher
saturated fat intake was found
to be associated with the development
of worse global cognitive function
and memory decline, an apparent
acceleration of brain aging
as if you were six years older.
How can we cut down
on saturated fat?
By cutting down on cheese,
cake, ice cream, and chicken,
essentially the top
sources in the American diet,
but also pork, burgers,
and beef in general.
In my video on the role of glycotoxins
in cognitive decline,
I profiled this study, showing
that just five days of a high-fat,
low-carb diet impairs
energy metabolism in the heart
as well as cognitive function,
concluding such diets
are detrimental to the
heart and brain.
Now, they were thinking
the impaired energy production
may have accounted for the
brain dysfunction as well,
but high levels of dietary
glycotoxins, so-called AGE’s,
are also associated with
cognitive decline,
so we may want
to cut down our intake
of baked, broiled, or grilled meat,
chicken, or fish,
as well as certain
dairy products.
But there’s another possibility.
“Metabolic Endotoxemia:
A Potential Underlying Mechanism
of the Relationship
between Dietary Fat Intake
and Risk for Cognitive
Impairments.”
Endotoxins are highly
pro-inflammatory components
of certain types of
bacteria like E. coli
that are released
when bacteria die,
and can end up being absorbed
through our gut wall
and end up in the bloodstream,
resulting in what’s called endotoxemia.
The highest levels of these
endotoxins are found,
not surprisingly, in foods
like meat that are contaminated
with bacteria, both
red meat and white meat.
And having elevated levels of
endotoxin circulating
in your blood stream may be
detrimental for healthy aging,
associated with
a large range of diseases,
such as obesity, type 2 diabetes,
heart disease, and depression.
Put people on a high-fat,
low-carb diet for five days,
and endotoxin levels in the blood stream
roughly double.
Endotoxin levels before
and after a few days
on a high-fat diet.
In fact, even a single meal
can do it.
Give people some sausage
and egg McMuffins
with hash browns, and you
can get a significant increase
within hours after the meal.
How do we know it wasn’t the refined carbs
in the muffin or something?
Because the control meal
had a muffin too,
but lower fat
and no sausage and egg.
In fact, you can have people
chug straight sugar water
and no change in endotoxin levels,
whereas there was a big jump
within hours drinking straight cream,
which is pretty much straight fat.
And not just any kind of fat,
but mostly saturated fat.
A double-blind, randomized
crossover trial demonstrated
that a single meal
high in saturated fat
can impede attention
(meaning the cognitive ability
to distinguish target stimuli
from distractors in a computer game),
compared with an identical meal
high in the kind of fat
found in nuts, seeds,
and avocados.
And this cognitive deficit
was present five hours after the meal,
and who knows how much
longer after that.
There are two ways to cut down
on endotoxin bursts after meals.
One is to not eat so many
in the first place.
But if you do eat meat and dairy,
the addition of fiber-rich foods
can blunt the endotoxin surge.
Same sausage and
egg McMuffin endotoxin bomb
but with or without Fiber
One cereal,
which would be
like 30 grams of fiber,
and it seemed
to glom onto the endotoxins,
preventing the bump of endotoxemia
three hours after the meal.
The fiber also reduced
the oxidative stress,
the free radicals
generated by such a meal,
showing clearly that the addition of fiber
to the high-fat, high-calorie meal
had profound effects on metabolic
and inflammatory events
after the meal.
And over time, meal after meal,
this could have long-term implications.
Recent investigations reported
higher abundance of endotoxins
in the brains of patients
with Alzheimer’s disease
on autopsy—endotoxins building up
in the memory center of the brain,
the region of the brain
that develops the earliest
and most profound neuropathology
in Alzheimer’s.
Some advanced Alzheimer's patients
had up to a 26-fold increase
in endotoxin levels over
age-matched controls without dementia.
And where were the
endotoxins concentrated?
Smack dab in the middle
of the amyloid plaques,
a pathology characteristic
of Alzheimer's.
The endotoxins are staining red here
and the amyloid staining green.
You can see how they superimpose
right over each other,
suggesting endotoxins may be
playing a role in the formation
of these plaques, like happens
in the brains of other animals.
For these and other reasons,
proper nutrition has been proposed
as a promising
non-medical strategy
to prevent cognitive decline
and subsequent dementia.